<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mike&#39;s Notebook</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mike&#39;s Notebook</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Retrieve EPA ECHO Data in R</title>
      <link>/2018/01/03/retrieve-epa-echo-data-in-r/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2018/01/03/retrieve-epa-echo-data-in-r/</guid>
      <description>EPA’s ECHO website is a useful tool for obtaining wastewater discharge data, in the form of Discharge Monitoring Reports (DMR). These DMRs provide the reported monitoring data from permitted dischargers in the form of effluent quantity and quality. These are useful data for water quality modeling, load allocations, and watershed characterization. However, downloading from the website is tedious at best, requiring clicking through multiple screens one permit at a time.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>About Michael Schramm I am an early career research professional specializing in water science and policy. I leverage spatial and data analytic tools that provide effective visual and written communication to bridge gaps between policy, science, and the public. Currently as a researcher at the Texas Water Resources Institute, I primarily lead projects aimed at improving surface water quality in coordination with state and local stakeholders. Primary research interests include (1) watershed based planning and sustainability, (2) environmental data visualization and communication, and (3) local and regional water and energy planning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time-series decomposition and trend analysis in Python</title>
      <link>/2015/08/01/simple-time-series-trend-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Aug 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2015/08/01/simple-time-series-trend-analysis/</guid>
      <description>There are a number of methods to accomplish time-series decompositions in R, including the decompose and STL commands.
I haven&amp;rsquo;t come across a seasonal decomposition method in Python comparable to R&amp;rsquo;s STL. However, statsmodels 0.6 added a naive seasonal decomposition method similar to R&amp;rsquo;s decompose that is not as powerful as the LOESS method used in STL. Let&amp;rsquo;s run through an example:
import urllib2 import datetime as datetime import pandas as pd import statsmodels.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>